Guide to the Margaret S. Mahler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
During the 1930s Mahler conducted Rorschach training for many American analysts who came to Vienna to study. Americans Margaret Ribble, Margaret Hawkins O'Neil and Helen Ross, all specialists in child delinquency, came to Vienna to train with Aichorn. In addition, Mahler lectured on and conducted Rorschach testing at the state university in Vienna. She collaborated with Judith Silberpfennig on a study of the Rorschach in diagnosing organic brain damage. Many of Mahler's early publications resulted from this project. Mahler organized the first psychoanalytic child guidance clinic (Ambulatorium Rauscher-Strasse) in Vienna and was the head from 1933-1938. In 1936 Mahler met and married Paul Mahler, a chemist, who was a junior partner in his family cordial factory. With the impending force of Nazism engulfing Germany and Austria, Mahler made efforts to leave Austria as early as January 1937. In 1938, Margaret and Paul Mahler left Austria and relocated in England, through the intervention of Lady Leontine Sassoon and the psychoanalysts of the Vienna Psychoanalytic Institute. The Mahlers were granted six month visas and authorization to continue their emigration to the United States. In England, Mahler conducted Rorschach tests, attended Anna Freud's seminars at the Hampstead Child Clinic, and studied English. In October 1938 Margaret and Paul Mahler set sail for the United States.
With the aid of American analysts and other European emigrés in New York City Mahler set about establishing her psychoanalytic practice. She was befriended by Caroline Zachary, then Director of the Bureau of Child Guidance of the New York City Board of Education and head of the Institute of Human Development. Mahler conducted Rorschach testing for Zachary at the IHD and its affiliate, the Educational Institute. Zachary introduced Mahler to Edith T. Schmidt and Benjamin Spock in 1939. It was Spock who first referred child patients to Mahler.
The New York psychoanalytic community did not welcome the recent emigrés. In 1939 an effort was made within the New York Psychoanalytic Society to encourage the emigrés to venture to other geographic locations to establish their practices. Mahler politely, but characteristically refused the idea that she should establish her practice in Elizabeth, New Jersey. Additionally, the emigrés were strongly urged not to practice psychoanalysis before obtaining their medical licenses. Mahler passed the state medical board exam on her first attempt. In 1940, she presented her paper "Pseudoimbecility: A Magic Cap of Invisibility" to the New York Psychoanalytic Society. She was accepted into the New York Psychoanalytic Society based on her presentation, and the Psychoanalytic Quarterly published the lecture. Mahler became the chief consultant to the New York State Psychiatric Institute, Children's Services at Columbia University and was appointed an associate in psychiatry at Columbia University. Mahler published papers, lectures and pamphlets pertaining to various aspects of child psychosis from 1942. In 1943 she published with Leo Rangell, in Psychiatric Quarterly, the results of a study they conducted on children with tics: "A Psychosomatic Study of Maladie des Tics" (Gilles de la Tourette's Disease). She published pamphlets for the New York State Committee on Mental Hygiene and lectured at various local aid societies including the New York School of Social Work, the Schilder Society and the Jewish Board of Guardians. Mahler spoke at professional associations as well, such as the New York Psychoanalytic Society, the American Psychoanalytic Association and the American Society for Research in Psychosomatic Medicine.
Mahler continued to work with children who had multiple tics and this led to the discovery that some children admitted to the New York State Psychiatric Institute became psychotic at puberty. In collaboration with Dr. Jean Luke, Mahler published in 1946 "Outcome of the Tic Syndrome" in the Journal of Nervous Mental Disease. In subsequent studies Mahler focused on childhood psychosis and its manifestations, presenting and publishing numerous papers on childhood psychosis in the late 1940s. In 1948 she presented her work with J.R. Ross and Zaira deFries at the American Orthopsychiatric Association and in 1949 published "Clinical Studies in Benign and Malignant Cases of Childhood Psychosis (Schizophrenia-like)."
In 1950 Mahler began to concentrate her research efforts on the study of child psychosis. She became affiliated in 1955 with the newly organized Albert Einstein College of Medicine at Yeshiva University, serving as the main consultant to children's services, as well as holding conferences on child psychosis. In 1959 she became a clinical professor in psychiatry. At this time she also became affiliated with the Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute where she was the chairperson of the child analysis training program from 1950-1960. Mahler also taught classes and conducted advanced seminars in child analysis. In addition, she supervised analyst trainees.
Mahler's research efforts centered in New York, where she and Manuel Furer, fellow Einstein faculty member, founded a therapeutic nursery for psychotic children. This nursery was established to continue the work Mahler began at the New York State Psychiatric Institute. In 1955 Mahler and Furer applied to the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) to support a study of the natural history of symbiotic child psychosis. At the time of this initial application, Mahler and Furer realized that the focus and resources of the newly established Albert Einstein College of Medicine would not support their research efforts. Upon being granted funding by the NIMH, Mahler and Furer returned that money, with the hope that once an appropriate site for the nursery was located, the NIMH would again fund the project. In 1956 two buildings at the Masters School in New York City became available which suited Mahler's research needs. Mahler and Furer reapplied to NIMH in 1959 and again received the initial funding they earlier returned.
The "Study of the Natural History of Symbiotic Child Psychosis" conducted at the Masters Children's Center from 1957-1964 began as a study of five very disturbed children and their mothers. Mahler discovered shortly after beginning the study that one child was psychotic and would require individual attention. The project was undertaken in the tripartite design meaning the child, therapist and mother became involved in the therapy. To supplement the work conducted by the therapist, the mother was also required to see a social worker involved with the study. Mahler's contention was that the child developed through a series of phases which allowed the child to begin to recognize itself as an individual entity from the mother. For reasons unknown to Mahler, some children did not carry out the steps which lead to individuality, or the steps were retarded for a particular reason. If the children did not move through these phases, they became deeply disturbed, some psychotic. Mahler reasoned that if the mother took an active role in the therapy, she could facilitate the process for the child. This relationship was crucial for allowing the child to develop a relatively normal symbiotic relationship with the mother, and then carry out the individuation and separation from the mother which the disturbed and psychotic children lacked.
Mahler's theory by which a child becomes an entity with a personal sense of identity was first reported in 1954 when she presented with Bert Gosliner, their work in "On Symbiotic Child Psychosis: Genetic, Dynamic and Restitutive Aspects." In 1960, Mahler and Furer reported their findings in "On the 'Symbiotic Syndrome' in Infantile Psychosis" at the Pan American Medical Congress. In 1968, On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation was published describing their findings from this study as well as subsequent studies relating to the development of the separation-individuation theory.
Questions arose from the Mahler/Furer study: Why does a relatively small percentage of children not firmly develop a sense of identity during the first three years? Why does the majority? When does this formation of identity take place? Mahler and Furer realized the need to conduct another study with a group of psychotic babies, their mothers and a control group of "normal" babies and their mothers. In 1962 the Field Foundation supported this pilot study which marked Mahler's transition from focusing on developing psychotic children to that of children with normal development. Mahler continued her studies with support from the NIMH. In 1960 Fred Pine joined the Masters Children's Center from the Hudson Guild Settlement, and John McDevitt joined the staff in 1965 from the Yale Child Study Center. With Pine and McDevitt, Mahler continued to conduct her studies on the development of the separation-individuation of the "normal" child. This "normal" study was conducted through the early 1970s, and the findings from this study were reported in the seminal work, The Psychological Birth of the Human Infant, published in 1974. After the publication of The Psychological Birth of the Human Infant Mahler continued to study the development of normal children. Work from the original study continues through the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation.
Mahler continued to present and publish her findings during the 1970s and early 1980s. Mahler delivered the Freud Anniversary Lecture at the New York Psychoanalytic Institute in 1971. The Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute honors Mahler with the Margaret S. Mahler Symposium Series. She was named visiting professor of child psychoanalysis at the Medical College of Pennsylvania and professor emerita of psychiatry at Columbia University in 1974. Mahler has received awards from the New York Psychoanalytic Society, the New York Psychoanalytic Institute, the American Psychiatric Association, the American Academy of Psychoanalysis, the New York Council on Child Psychiatry, and she has been honored by many other institutions of higher education. Margaret S. Mahler died in October 1985 at the age of eight-eight. In August 1986, her ashes were placed with her husband's next to her mother and father's gravesite in the Jewish Cemetery in Sopron, Hungary.
Child development; Child psychology; Infant psychology; Psychoanalysts; Psychoses in children; Separation-individuation; Tourette syndrome; Aichorn, August; Blanck, Gertrude; Blanck, Rubin; Blos, Peter; Blum, Harold P., 1929-; Brazelton, T. Berry, 1918-; Call, Justin D.; Elkisch, Paula; Ferenczy, Béni; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982; Furer, Manuel; Greenacre, Phyllis; Greenson, Ralph R. (Ralph Romeo), 1911-1979; Harley, Marjorie; Hoffer, Willi; Kaplan, Louise J.; Lebovici, Serge, 1915-2000; Mahler, Margaret S.; McDevitt, John; Neubauer, Peter B.; Pine, Fred, 1931-; Rangell, Leo; Sandler, Joseph; Settlage, Calvin F., 1921-; Albert Einstein College of Medicine; American Academy of Child Psychiatry; American Psychiatric Association; American Psychoanalytic Association; Columbia University. College of Physicians and Surgeons; International Association for Child Psychiatry and Allied Professions; Medical College of Pennsylvania; New York Psychoanalytic Institute; Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1918-1985; Series I; 10.5 linear feet (28 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or subject. Mahler's outgoing correspondence, address book, calendars and diaries are located at the end of this series.
  - A: General Correspondence, 1942-1949,1953-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Abelin, Ernest, 1966, 1970, 1972-1978, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Abrams, Jules, 1972, 1974, 1975, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Abuzzahab, F.S., 1969-1970, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aichorn, August, 1938, 1945, 1948-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1955-1963, 1966-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10-17)
    - Activities, 1955-1968, 1974-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 18-25)
    - Bronx Municipal Hospital center, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Bronx Municipal Hospital center, 1959-1975 (Box 2, Folder 28-33)
    - Center for Pre-School Children, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - In-Patient Conference, 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Proposal for Research Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Therapeutic Nursery School, 1956-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - American Academy of Child Psychiatry, 1972-1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, Inc., 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - American Handbook of Psychiatry, 1956-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - American Orthopsychiatric Association, Inc., 1950-1952, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - American Psychiatric Association, 1948, 1958-1983, 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association, 1963-1985 (Box 2, Folder 43-47)
    - Conference-Denver, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 43-47)
    - Conference-New York, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 43-47)
    - Conference-Quebec, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43-47)
  - American Psychotherapy Seminar, 1976-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - American Red Cross, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Anthony, Dr. E James, 1965-1982 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Antunes, John L., 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Arlow, Jacob A., 1972-1983 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Aronson, Jason: reception, 1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Association for Child Psychoanalysis, Inc., 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Astley, Royden, 1961, 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Atlantic Monthly, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Austen Riggs Center, Inc., 1955-1985 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Awards: Albert Einstein Award, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Awards: American Psychiatric Association, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Awards: Barnard Medal of Distinction, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Awards: Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Awards: Medical College of Pennsylvania Appointment, 1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Awards: New York Society of Freudian Psychologists, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Awards, 1969-1983 undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - B: General Correspondence, 1935-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 65-69)
  - Babcock, Charlotte, 1958-1978 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Baker, Doris, 1976-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Bak, Robert C., 1968, 1974, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Balint, Alice, 1938, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Balint, Emilie and Micheal, 1956-1957,1972 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Balint, Emma; Blau, Barton, 1946-1959 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Baltimore Psychoanalytic Institute; Baltimore Pyschoanalytic Society, Baltimore-District of Columbia Society for Psychoanalysis, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Barnard Medal of Distinction, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Basic Books, 1973-1985 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Basel, Barbara and Gunther, 1970-1985 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Bellak, Leopold, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Ben-Aaron, Miriam, 1967-1977 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Beres, David, 1956,1962 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Bergman, Anni, 1966-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Bergman, Lisa, 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Bergman, Maria and Martin, 1968-1978 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Birthday Celebration, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Birthdays, 1978, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Blanck, Gertrude and Rubin, 1971-1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Blomfield, Dr. O. H. D., 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Blos, Merta, 1969-1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Blos, Peter, 1970-1985 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Blum, Harold P., 1973-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Bogicevic, Anne Marie, 1958-1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Books: Festschrift, 1967-1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Books: Festschrift McDevitt-Contributors, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Books: On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation: General Correspondence, 1968-1976 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Books: On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation: Newman, Lottie, 1967,1968 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Books: On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation: Translations; Dutch, French, Italian, 1969-1977 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Books: On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation: Translation; German, 1969-1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Books: On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation: Translation; Spanish, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: General Correspondence, 1973-1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 101-103)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: Foreign Editions; General, 1975-1983 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: Foreign Editions; British, 1975,1979 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: Foreign Editions; French, 1975-1981 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: Foreign Editions; German, 1974-1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: Mandelstam, Charles, attorney, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: Paperback, 1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Books: Psychological Birth of the Human Infant: Permissions, 1973,1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Books: Selected Papers [2 vols]: General Correspondence, 1976-1978, undated (Box 5, Folder 111-113)
  - Books: Selected Papers [2 vols]: Permissions, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Brazelton, T. Berry, 1982, 1983, 1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Brill Lecture, 1961, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Brill Library-Lists of Acquisitions, 1962, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Brill Library, 1972-1985 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Brookfield, Connecticut, 1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Bry, Ava M., 1975-1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Bry, Gerhard and Thea, 1975-1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Burland, J. Alexis, 1968, 1973-1977, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - C: General Correspondence, 1938-1973 (Box 5, Folder 123-124)
  - C: General Correspondence, 1974-1985, undated (Box 6, Folder 125-126)
  - California, 1974, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - Call, Justin D., 1968-1985 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Cambridge Hospital; Continuing Education Division, Department of Psychiatry, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Castro de Padro, Teresa, 1966-1985, undated (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Center for Advanced Psychoanalytic Study [CAPS]-Group Four, 1964-1971 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Center for Advanced Psychoanalytic Study [CAPS]-Group Eight, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Chestnut Lodge, 1966-1982 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Chicago Conference on Early Child Development, 1964, undated (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - Chodorow, Nancy, 1981, 1984, undated (Box 6, Folder 135)
  - Clinics, Child Guidance Centers, 1954, 1958, undated (Box 6, Folder 136)
  - Collins, Harold, 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - Colorado Juvenile Council, 1978, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - Columbia University; College of Physicians and Surgeons, Department of Psychiatry, 1954-1984 (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Columbia University, 1943-1956,1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Condolences, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 141-142)
  - Connecticut Postgraduate Seminar in Psychiatry and Neurology, 1953-1957 (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - Czettel, Arpádné, and Gizi, 1980-1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 144)
  - Crowther, Mary, 1966-1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 145)
  - Cuban National Congress of Neurology and Psychiatry, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 146)
  - de Cuevas, John, 1971-1984 (Box 6, Folder 147)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1938-1979 (Box 7, Folder 148-149)
  - Herczegh, Arthurné and Irma, 1943-1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 150-151)
  - Czettel, J. E., 1945, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - D: General Correspondence, 1942-1985, undated (Box 7, Folder 153-154)
  - Daily Routine, 1965,1979 (Box 7, Folder 155)
  - Davidoff-Hirsch, Helen, 1977-1983 (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - De Menil, Dominique, 1975-1985, undated (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - De Menil, George and Louis, 1972-1980, undated (Box 7, Folder 158)
  - Deri, Peter, 1984,undated (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - Deri, Susan, 1979-1982, undated (Box 7, Folder 160)
  - Dictating Machine, 1954, 1962, undated (Box 7, Folder 161)
  - Dormandi, Olga, 1956, 1959, undated (Box 7, Folder 162)
  - Dupont, Judith, 1971-1985 (Box 7, Folder 163)
  - Dworschak, Rosi, 1958, 1971, 1975-1985, undated (Box 7, Folder 164-167)
  - E: General Correspondence, 1944, 1954-1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 168-169)
  - Eastern Pennsylvania Psychiatric Institute, 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Edward, Joyce, 1976-1984 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - Eissler, K. R., 1946, 1953, 1967, 1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 172)
  - Elkisch, Paula, 1957-1981, undated (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Ellmer [Smith], Paula, 1958, 1974, 1981, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - Endler, Norman, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Erikson Institute for Early Education, 1974-1978, undated (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - Essex County Overbrook Hospital, 1956-1965 (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Europe 1974, 1974, undated (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Europe 1975, 1974, 1975, undated (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - Europe 1977 (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - F: General Correspondence, 1955-1985, undated (Box 8, Folder 181-182)
  - Fabian, Pablo, 1943, 1946, 1971, 1974, undated (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - Fagan, Ann, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 184)
  - Feilendorf, Stefanie, 1925-1938 (Box 8, Folder 185)
  - Ferenczy, Beni and Erszi, 1945-1980 (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Fleming, Joan, 1965-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 187)
  - Floor Plan: 10 West 66th Street, undated (Box 8, Folder 188)
  - Foundation's Fund for Research, 1972-1976 (Box 8, Folder 189)
  - Franz Alexander Memorial Lecture, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 190)
  - Freud Museum, 1984,1985, undated (Box 8, Folder 191)
  - Freud, Anna, 1954-1960 (Box 8, Folder 192)
  - Freud, W. Ernst, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 193)
  - Fried, Edrita, 1957-1980 (Box 8, Folder 194)
  - Frijling-Schreuder, E. C. M., 1968-1980 (Box 8, Folder 195)
  - Furer, Manuel, 1956-1981 (Box 8, Folder 196)
  - G: General Correspondence, 1949-1985 (Box 8, Folder 197-199)
  - Gaddini de Benedetti, Renata, 1969-1983, undated (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Gaines, Nan, undated (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Gale, Clara, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Galenson, Eleanor, 1971-1985, undated (Box 9, Folder 203)
  - Ginn Custom Publishing, 1980-1983 (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Gondor, Emery I., 1952, 1956, 1958, 1961, undated (Box 9, Folder 205)
  - Gordon, Bianca, 1963-1976 (Box 9, Folder 206)
  - Gordon, Judith, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 207)
  - Greenacre, Phyllis, 1958-1982, undated (Box 9, Folder 208)
  - Greenson, Hildi and Ralph, 1970-1985, undated (Box 9, Folder 209)
  - Greenspan, Stanley, 1977-1981 (Box 9, Folder 210)
  - Gregoire, Marion, 1971, undated (Box 9, Folder 211)
  - H: General Correspondence, 1940-1984, undated (Box 9, Folder 212-213)
  - Hardy, Nicholas P., 1975-1977 (Box 9, Folder 214)
  - Harley, Marjorie, 1968-1985, undated (Box 9, Folder 215)
  - Harrison, Saul, 1956-1978 (Box 9, Folder 216)
  - Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 217)
  - Hawaii: 1966, 1965, 1966, undated (Box 9, Folder 218)
  - Heinz Hartman Award, 1975-1977 (Box 9, Folder 219)
  - Institute Albert-Prévost, 1940-1958, undated (Box 9, Folder 220)
  - Herskovitz, Herbert H., 1953-1970 (Box 9, Folder 221)
  - Hoffer, Willi, 1941-1976 (Box 9, Folder 222)
  - Hoffner, Gabor and BÅni, 1969-1973 (Box 9, Folder 223)
  - Holtz, Sibylla, 1975-1985, undated (Box 9, Folder 224)
  - Holtz, Ursel, 1970-1983, undated (Box 9, Folder 225)
  - Hornick, Edward, Jay, and Margaret, 1969-1984, undated (Box 9, Folder 226)
  - Hospitals and Sanitariums, 1957-1961 (Box 9, Folder 227)
  - Hudson Guild Anniversary Letter, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 228)